welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
oh okay
so let's do some check-ins feeling uh
excited
a tad apprehensive is Bonita just
mention something about the session but
yeah excited like a giddy excitement so
welcome to the stoah i am peter
lindbergh
the stuart of the stoah and the stoah is
a place for us to cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this moment and so I'm inviting
all these interesting people to come in
and then test and experiment with
different kind of psycho technologies
and so Bonita and I were gonna workshop
something think about a session to do at
this Doha and we didn't have time to
kind of meet so he said let's just use a
psycho technology playground I'm like
okay cool so who threw something in the
calendar and then we were supposed to
meet you know 15 minutes before just to
kind of run over it but Bonita was in a
different room room and my computer
wasn't working it's like we just met
each other like two minutes ago before
we started letting people in so we I
have no idea what's gonna happen and I
kind of liked it that way so that being
said I will hand it over to Bonita
[Music]
all of a sudden watching this screen
populate phrase came to my mind we are
making history
someone sucks a bird set in my head we
are making history and then I thought
it's not like just another page right
it's just these are all brand new
chapters here in this in this book yeah
so we're gonna do some untested a couple
of tested things but we're going to
start with something untested in the
virtual world
and that is what's making Peter nervous
so we want to all when when I say so
we're gonna all unmute ourselves and
we're going to sing our name into the
space and we'll do that three times
then we'll mute ourselves will be a
second round will mute ourselves and
them be a final round okay
very easy all right so is that for me so
everyone has the option to unmute
themselves so yeah so unmute yourselves
and the count of three you're going to
sing your name into this space Limburg
that's a good start
so second on the second on the second
try
one two three
[Applause]
[Music]
oh now hold the last note as I go like
this okay this is hard for Stoics you
don't have a sense of humor one last
time hold to know as I speak two three
[Music]
so that's a pulse that will go out past
the solar system and past you know SETI
it's going out faster than set t then
will be heard for the second round
you're gonna sing where you're from so
city and state and then hold the note
and we'll do that three times one two
three
[Music]
okay this is just the warmup now we're
just gonna sing who are name and where
we're from and we'll just one time and
just stretch that out that last note one
two three
[Music]
okay thank you very much you commute now
okay so we're gonna start with a Daoist
Cohen so you know the Daoists don't have
Cohen's but this is a Daoist Cohen and a
Daoist Cohen is something you don't try
to solve with your mind you've tried to
solve with your body that's what makes
it a Daoist Cohen so we're going to do
this is another brief warm-up exercise
and then we'll get to the real cycle
technology so these are just kind of
getting us into the main meal
I've been burping a lot on the Internet
so let me just mute myself
okay so if you can stand up if you do if
you can't if you can't stand up because
you know you're attached to this
equipment then sit down but put your
feet firmly on the ground and kind of
stomp so you can your body knows my feet
are on the ground so some of you are
dancing that's cool but we're gonna end
up you can move your body but you want
your feet to feel on the ground really
kind of heavy they are on the ground
right so just feel the earth the earth
is holding up your feet your feet are on
the ground okay so everybody's got that
sensation that your feet are on the
ground now I'm going to ask you two
questions the first question is where
are your feet
okay so we can sum someone can answer on
the ground on the ground good job okay
second question where is your head
in this guy on my neck in the clouds so
that's the Cohen does anybody have
another what are the other answers on
the ground on the ground very good
you
okay that was our warm-up did you get a
chance to ask people to bring like scrap
paper or sticky or email yeah it's not
necessary for this this exercise but it
creates more of an embodied experience
you
I think at least one of you have done
this with me before maybe not can't
remember okay so what I want you to do
is
observe something in your mind observe
something you know think of something
you know could be a big thing could be a
little thing just something you know and
write it down or write down a little
word that refers to that knowing
you
Peter I'm gonna rely on you to paste
this okay so you can just kind of get a
sense of what I would move on
thank you
okay now on that piece of paper I want
you to crumple that piece of paper up
and throw it away
you
there you go there's one out of a
billion
so we're gonna purge these things so now
write down the first thing that comes in
your mind that you know write it down on
the piece of paper
you
crumple that paper up and throw it away
feels good don't it one more time
something that you know something that
pops in your head that you know
you can hold on to it a little time
investigate your relationship with this
knowledge feel the weight of it
and then just throw it away
air goes awesome you guys are really
good at this
okay now when I think I want you to
think of something you're afraid of one
of your fears
write it down could be a big thing could
be a little thing doesn't matter
you
I want you to massage that fear
spend a little time with it
feel its texture
rather than crumple it up and throw it
away
you
I want you to think of something else
you fear write it down
could be a big thing could be a little
thing
you
and hold that fear in your hands and
send it love
all the love you have
so much love it becomes sacred
and then crumple it up and just throw it
away
you
one last fear something that's got you
by the balls
write that one down it tried to get away
you
this one you're going to face
and give it respect
you
and then crumple it up and throw it away
this last one is more difficult
I want you to write something
some question you have
you
and this one I want you to tear into a
million tiny little pieces
you
and let them fall like rain drops into
the sea
you
another question
one that you're working on just before
you came here man maybe one you don't
want to give up
one that's writing your book
you
and tear it into little pieces
and scatter it
like ashes of the deceased
you
now I want you to write one final
question
I want you to write Who am I
you
and I want you to rip that into a
million pieces and throw it like dust
into the wind
the final liberation
the quest to know who you are
the unsolvable mystery of it
you
so before we go on could we have do we
have the capacity for reflections I mean
it's a great big group I think so
which is a people to go off mute yeah
yeah so if we want four or five minutes
of reflection if everyone silent we'll
just move on that was the first part of
it
this was beautiful and weird and
beautifully weird it reminds me of a
sort of spoken word poem by woman named
T fairy to those who weren't as lucky
and it involves little bits of paper as
a anchor or focus with that and I'll
post a link enough
I'm curious about what's left after I've
thrown out all of my fears and my
deepest questions there's an emptiness
left that's not exactly empty there's
something left of me here okay so now we
can move on because that's exactly the
second part we want to examine our
experience and we will know there's we
know certain aspects of the our
experience so we're not going we're not
that interested in reporting about body
sensations or perception sounds taste
touch any body sensations we're
interested in what's appearing in your
mind let's say and so as you watch what
comes into your mind
there will be knowings there will be
fears and there will be questions and
just as Donna said this exercise is
spend some time to make sure there's not
something other than those three that's
in your experience we're looking for
something that's not annoying not a fear
not a question that's in that space that
room of your experience
so we're going to spend ten minutes
we'll ask if there's more questions or
clarification around this the
instruction
and if so then we'll clarify a little
and then we will share
and as we go along if I Intuit something
I might give a little more instruction
but we're looking not for body
sensations or a perception we're looking
in the room of our experience something
that's not a question a knowing or a
fear and as those arise you can
virtually you know throw them out use
that kind of
feeling of what we were doing and we'll
want to know what else is arising
your experience
you
do you want us to speak about those
funny oh not yet if if you have a
question put it in the chat so I'm not
sure this was a question about the
actual experience but someone wrote on
having resistance resistance is a bodily
sensation so that's we're still looking
for something different than that these
are all these are all good noticing yes
resistance is in your experience that
comes from your body contraction neural
chemicals so I'll check the chat if
people are yeah yes yes Dan and not up
not a perception like a sound or smell
yes Sharon so hold on to that and just
investigate that the quality of that a
little better a little more I'm watching
the chat yes Natalia hold on to that so
joy is a bodily sensation as I'm
describing it here so continue to look
for something else in your experience
Annie you're onto something it's a
metaphor
things like kinship is also a bodily
sensations you know it's a effect
frustration also that's good good
noticing where we're looking is in the
same place where the knowings the fear
and the questions come we're looking in
that space of experience
yes so Raya we're going to ask you to
unpack that your answer if you just
remember at some point
also yours Peter
you
wondering is a state of questioning
ah so Sarah we're going to ask you to
unpack that it's a loaded loaded word
you
about five more minutes just keeps keep
looking to see if you are missing
something that's so obvious it's hidden
in plain sight
something in your experience
as you keep looking there's a thought no
and there's this and there's heart
feeling that's in from my body sensation
melts what else is in your experience
you
you know the sadness is in your body
body sensation in this exercise
you
okay been a worgen I'm going to ask you
some questions first
should I eat myself yeah okay so just
share what you wrote you say you said
what did you say I said I can't find
anything that seems like it would fit
the criteria emphasis on thing yes
you
good what do you mean by you can't find
just just talk around that well it seems
like the categories are comprehensively
exhaustive of what arises in experience
in this
in that moment I see okay that's and
that's annoying and there's a
fluctuating sense of credence and that
and that's a sensation and then I
questioned that and that's a question
[Music]
and then like there's no way to
so things seem to look back on
themselves
what's happening right now
it's a bit like I'm looking for
something that's just on my periphery
and ah you're looking for something is
that annoying
don't think so well you said I'm looking
for something the experience of looking
is that unknowing may be a question is
it a question
it's a looking for
yeah but I just analytically it seems
like that could be Syd seemed under the
categories given unless I do yeah
analytically you could recursive you
could recur on it but when you're just
authentically looking in that moment is
that one of those categories in your
experience
I think it could be depending on how you
construe those categories and and I'm
looking yeah but when you're looking
is the looking a category in your
experience I'm not asking you a question
I'm asking in the moment that you're
looking
you can then turn it into a category in
your experience
so Sharon what do you want to elaborate
on that does your carrying this forward
just as you were working through it with
Ben I realized that the the process of
looking was like an activity in my mind
and metaphorically it's an expression
like like if I was looking for my car
keys I'd be turning over cushions and no
it's not that and it's not this and I
can't use that one and that won't start
the car and so there's this process of
what I'm doing in my mind so that that
just came up as you were talking to Ben
and focusing on looking
you
but that that isn't a knowing and it
isn't necessarily a sensation unless I
try to speak about it metaphorically
then it becomes a body sensation yeah so
that's a good way to get out of the
infinite recursive 'ti of the question
if I'm looking for car keys the looking
is nice and I find a pillow or a book or
this the looking is neither a pillow or
a book or the car keys
that's not those categories it is just
the process that's that the experience
is it's a verb it's a verb right yeah so
then else want to language that in the
way they're understanding it
it's a gerund yes
that's we use it as a it's a verb that
we use in the sentence as if it were
known the looking but in experience in
actual in the process of it verbing it's
not a noun then we capture as a noun
yeah someone got an A in English in high
school we need their what I was
experiencing is feeling into the
sensation of knowingness and then
feeling into the sensation of
unknowingness and then having this
desire of wanting to know which almost
has a controlling element to it and then
when you're talking to been the the
looking miss is very close to the
listening miss that I was mentioning
previously yeah I when you put that I
found it to be similar to looking or
listening the listening is the process
by which
yeah it seems there is a another level
to listening because you're receiving
something as well more than just sort of
um I guess more information doesn't feel
quite right but something something
there so what I'm trying to get at and
then we're gonna have the last we got a
build on this this is just to get so
we're talking about the same thing that
we're gonna want to examine so we build
these to get deeper and deeper they get
more subtle and subtle so what I want to
highlight is if you had the experience
of listening so listening for what was
in your experience that was none of
those or attending to attending to
something in your experience or looking
for that you actually were not this not
not this not that so if we could get
agreement that at least that's what the
exercise entailed that activity that
gerund earnest that I'm just gonna call
movement even the listening is kind of
like moving into the space right so some
kind of process or gerund like verb or
I'm just gonna call it movement there's
a certain movement quality
question.what I want us to do now is to
examine that it's a second level of
metacognition or a third
and one way you can do that is you could
put two thoughts in your head
and notice what moves as you think one
and then the other or one and then the
other or we want to get a handle on the
movement that is discerning what's in
your experience so you first experienced
that there's a moving around or moving
from attending to this to attending to
that and then try to examine that
movement itself
we'll go right - yeah we'll go hello
you
yes Stephanie that's it great noticing
you can really work with that because it
gives you a contrast
yeah Sharon it's not it's it's not
unusual that it goes away because you've
exhausted the the neural net you're
using it's like when you exhaust your
after image or something like that so
you can just relax or that just four
more minutes
okay he's Peter if you think we're ready
we could have some shares of questions
sounds good
someone talked about focusing and
blurring yeah there's uh the movement
can't get to like an expansion
contraction kind of
you
so if we want to share or continue
working it's up to you what this is
quite an advanced meditation
you
it's it's been resolved in different
ways in the traditions
but I think the interpretation is up for
grabs in our modern world
you
so if you read someone like Evan
Thompson he has
modern
modern re-examination of some of this or
Dan Brown's book on metacognition
these are competing modern
interpretations
you
if you got a room full of view if you
populated the store with meditators from
different traditions you'd have a what
will recall the first-tier food fight
over the interpretation of this
experience of course they go into the
experience much more much more power of
concentration and discernment they can
hold distinctions between the cognition
and the metacognition with much more
affect effectiveness
so we need to respect what they have to
say
you
sounds like a second-tier food fight
makes for a good psycho technology
you
it's also a good way you know it's in
the opposite direction of transcendental
meditation which is to relax your mind
into a calm state and this is we exhaust
we exhaust our neural net so we can't
think of anything for the next half-hour
so so it's kind of in the other
direction
you
I something please hmm I guess my
perception of whatever was going on is
that I kept trying to look at my
perception look keep framing it framing
it and like you said it was hard to hold
it and differentiate and then but then
I'm also looking at my differentiation
um
this deeply human need to find patterns
explain it but even that explaining was
coming from different levels of that
differentiation so it was muddy it was
messy it wasn't clear but yeah I it that
discernment that you spoke of it seems
like it's it needs practice like it's
it's it's not just come now I could see
that it was it's yeah there's there's
very interesting yeah it just reminded
me your reflection I might just I got a
new metaphor may or may not be helpful
but it reminded me of like you're trying
to study something very very small and
powerful like the like the photon but
your instrument scatters the photon and
then you you know and you're constantly
just before you can hold that
yes and I'm not sure if that's what you
meant but that's the image I got the
instrument itself has to be subtle
or else it's to course and it scatters
what you're looking for and that that
feeling of infinite recursion is a
scattering it's actually you you've
created layers of complexity and now
you've got to start over again it's like
a little bit of a cat-and-mouse game but
every time the cat swipes the mouse
there's five more mice yeah yeah so
that's you know these are not fancy
words but it's it's beautiful because
that is the nature of your what you were
experiencing and that is the
metacognitive muscle and if you were in
a traditional Dharma Society I would
have responded with a lot of big words
and mythological kind of explanations
and you you wouldn't quite actually know
where you were at it's a great business
model because then you have to spend
like 15 20 years to learn the language
and make those distinctions but yeah
Bonita in staying with that the movement
that you asked us to stay with the not
from thing to thing but the movement in
between so it feels the experiences of
being in the in-between of mm-hmm
so it's the movement that's just the
state of flux not any one thing but the
actual movement like I like I think that
there's something about that that I like
and it's like yeah like I I want to stay
in the movement so was that Stephanie I
had this chat in front of your face
Donna Donna yeah so then the the
esoteric question there is yeah so I
really appreciate what you say and
that that speaks to me I'm a process
philosopher when everything boils down
to movement I'm a taoist you know in
Taoism if an immovable object meets an
unstoppable force it's very clear that
the object moves right but some of the
traditions have an interpretation where
you're the stillness in the
the space of awareness through which
things move I find that as a very very
subtle scatter right so you're creating
an object like we talked about
Yoshio was talking about then more
things happen and I tend to think that
that interpretation creates a structural
level that is constructed is very subtly
constructed that you don't need the
space of awareness in which things move
I just so these are these are very very
sophisticated hair-splitting
conversations that the Buddha
scholastics enter into
thank you
cool we probably should wrap up soon
before I make some closing announcements
too many did you have any final words
you'd like to leave us with no I mean
this is delightful
I'd had a really nice rhythm no this
just it was just delightful and and you
know Peter you're doing such a fantastic
job there's a lot of excitement running
around the Twittersphere about how
exciting this work you're doing is for
everyone and I really appreciate being
invited to play in a moment of there's
some closing thoughts but yeah I'm
really really glad that we had that
disconnect technically beforehand and I
just totally handed the keys to you
do whatever you wanted here because it
was a really beautiful experience so
thank you so much Bonita for coming in
today
and thank you for everyone to you know
going on this wild ride with us for the
last hour
so next two events at the the stoah if
you just go to the store CA we have a
Q&A on the liminal war the rise of info
militias with Jack Murphy that's 4 p.m.
eastern time and then at 7:00 p.m.
Eastern Time we have Socratic
speed-dating with Raven Connolly and
that's really cool like mixing speed
dating technique with the Socratic
inquiry it's platonic but you can fall
in love with whoever you want to fall in
love with the store does not please love
and lastly the the stoah operates on a
gift economy I view this as a gift for
all of us to freely use in this time of
need if you're inspired to give a gift
to the stoah you can do so by going on
the website checking out the information
on the gift economy at the bottom
alright thank you everyone have a great
day thank you so much I'll probably see
you soon maybe I'm lucky